Newspapers are dying for a few reasons.
الصحف اليومية تموت لعدة أسباب
Readers don't want to pay for yesterday's news, and advertisers follow them.
القراء لا يرغبون بشراء أخبار الأمس، والمعلنين يتبعونهم
Your iPhone, your laptop,
الأي فون، والكمبيوتر المحمول الخاص بك
is much more handy than New York Times on Sunday.
أكثر عملية من صحيفة نيويورك تايمز يوم الأحد
And we should save trees in the end.
وفي النهاية من المرجح أنك أنقذت الأشجار
So it's enough to bury any industry.
وذلك كافي لإنهاء أية صناعة
So, should we rather ask, "Can anything save newspapers?"
ولذلك قد نتسائل، "هل يمكننا إنقاذ الصحف اليومية"؟
There are several scenarios for the future newspaper.
هناك عدة سيناريوهات لصحف المستقبل
Some people say it should be free;
بعض الناس يقولون، أنها يجب أن تكون مجانية
it should be tabloid, or even smaller: A4;
أنها يجب أن تكون بحجم التابلويد، وربما أصغر كحجم الأي٤
it should be local, run by communities,
أنها يجب أن تكون محلية، تدار من قبل المجتمعات
or niche, for some smaller groups like business --
أو متخصصة، موجهة لمجموعات أصغر كالأعمال -ـ
but then it's not free; it's very expensive.
ولكن في تلك الحالة الصحف لن تكون مجانية، بل أكثر غلاءاً
It should be opinion-driven;
يجب أن تكون موجهة بالرأي
less news, more views.
أخبار أقل، وأكثر آراء
And we'd rather read it during breakfast,
وأننا سنقرأها أثناء وجبة الفطور
because later we listen to radio in a car,
لأننا لاحقاً سنستمع للراديو في السيارة
check your mail at work and in the evening you watch TV.
أو ستقوم بقراءة بريدك في العمل، أو ستشاهد التلفاز مساءاً
Sounds nice, but this can only buy time.
يبدو ذلك جيداً، ولكنه فقط سيعطي الصحف بعض الوقت
Because in the long run,
لأنه على المدى البعيد
I think there is no reason, no practical reason
أعتقد أنه لايوجد سبب، لا سبب عملي
for newspapers to survive.
للصحف أن تنجو
So what can we do?
بالتالي ما الذي يمكننا عمله؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Let me tell you my story.
دعوني أخبركم قصتي
20 years ago, Bonnier, Swedish publisher,
منذ عشرين عام، مجموعة بونير، شركة نشر سويدية
started to set newspapers in the former Soviet Bloc.
افتتحت عدد من الصحف في دويلات ما كان يعرف بالإتحاد السوفيتي
After a few years, they had several newspapers in central and eastern Europe.
بعد عدد من السنوات، كانت المجموعة تمتلك عدد من الصحف في أوربا الوسطى والشرقية
They were run by an inexperienced staff,
هذه الصحف كانت تدار بواسطة عمالة رخيصة
with no visual culture, no budgets for visuals --
لا يمتلكون ثقافة بصرية، ولا ميزانية مخصصة للفنون البصرية
in many places there were not even art directors.
في فروع عديدة لم يكن هناك أي مدير للفن
I decided to be -- to work for them as an art director.
قررت أن أكون.. أن أعمل كمدير للفنون لهؤلاء
Before, I was an architect, and my grandmother asked me once,
سابقاً، كنت معماري، وسألتني جدتي مره
"What are you doing for a living?"
ما الذي تعمله لتكسب الرزق؟
I said, "I'm designing newspapers."
أجبتها، "أنا أصمم الصحف"
"What? There's nothing to design there. It's just boring letters"
ماذا؟ لا يوجد هناك شيء للتصميم. إنها فقط مجموعة رسائل مملة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And she was right. I was very frustrated, until one day.
وقد كانت على حق. كنت محبط جداً، حتى أحد الأيام
I came to London, and I've seen performance by Cirque du Soleil.
قدمت إلى لندن، وشاهدت عرض "سيركو دو سوليل"ـ
And I had a revelation. I thought,
وكان الوحي، كما أعتقد
"These guys took some creepy,
هذه المجموعة أخذت مجموعة من العروض العادية
run-down entertainment,
المتهالكة
and put it to the highest possible level of performance art."
ووصلت بها إلى أقصى درجة من الأداء الفني
I thought "Oh my God, maybe I can do the same with these boring newspapers."
وفكرت "يا إلهي، من الممكن أن أفعل ذات الشيء مع الصحف المملة"ـ
And I did. We started to redesign them, one by one.
وذلك ما فعلت. قمنا بإعادة تصميمهم، واحدة تلو الأخرى
The front page became our signature.
الصفحة الأولى أصبحت توقيعنا
It was my personal intimate channel to talk to the readers.
كانت قناتي الخاصة والتي أتواصل من خلالها مع القراء
I'm not going to tell you stories about teamwork or cooperation.
أنا لن أخبركم قصص عن العمل كفريق واحد والتعاون
My approach was very egotistic.
توجهي كان أناني بشدة
I wanted my artistic statement,
أردت رسالتي الفنية
my interpretation of reality.
ترجمتي ونظرتي للواقع
I wanted to make posters, not newspapers.
أردت إنتاج ملصقات، وليست صحف
Not even magazines: posters.
ولا حتى مجلات: ملصقات
We were experimenting with type,
كنّا نجرب الخطوط
with illustration, with photos. And we had fun.
مع الخيال، مع الصور، واستمتعنا كثيراً
Soon it started to bring results.
بسرعة بدأنا نرى النتائج
In Poland, our pages were named
في بولندا، صفحاتنا تم تسميتها
"Covers of the Year" three times in a row.
غلاف السنة ثلاث مرات متتالية
Other examples you can see here are from
أمثلة أخرى يمكنكم رؤيتها هنا هي من
Latvia, Lithuania, Estonia
لاتفيا، ليثونيا، أستونيا -ـ
and central European countries.
في دول أوربا الوسطى
But it's not only about the front page.
لكن ذلك ليس متعلقاً بالصفحة الأولى فقط
The secret is that we were treating
السر يكمن في أننا تعاملنا
the whole newspaper as one piece,
مع الصحيفة ككل على أنها قطعة واحدة
as one composition -- like music.
كمؤلف واحد -- مثل الموسيقى
And music has a rhythm, has ups and downs.
والموسيقى لها إيقاع، فيه صعود ونزول
And design is responsible for this experience.
والتصميم هو المسؤول عن هذا الشعور
Flipping through pages is readers experience,
تقليب الصفحات هي تجربة القراء
and I'm responsible for this experience.
وأنا مسؤول عن هذه التجربة
We treated two pages, both spreads, as a one page,
عاملنا الصفحتين، كلا المتقابلتين، على أنها صحفة واحدة
because that's how readers perceive it.
لأن القارئ يعاملها بهذه الطريقة
You can see some Russian pages here which got many awards
هنا يمكنكم رؤية صفحات بالروسية حصّلت على عدد من الجوائز
on biggest infographic competition in Spain.
في أكبر منافسة لتصوير المعلومات في أسبانيا
But the real award came from Society for Newspaper Design.
ولكن الجائزة الحقيقة كانت من مجتمع تصميم الصحف
Just a year after redesigning this newspaper in Poland,
فقط بعد سنة من إعادة تصميم هذه الصحيفة في بولندا
they name it the World's Best-Designed Newspaper.
قاموا بتسميتها أفضل صحيفة تصميماً في العالم
And two years later,
وبعد سنتين
the same award came to Estonia.
نفس الجائزة أتت إلى إستونيا
Isn't amazing?
أليس ذلك مدهشاً؟
What really makes it amazing: that the circulation of these newspapers
الشيء المدهش حقاً: أن توزيع هذه الصحف
were growing too.
كان يزيد أيضاً
Just some examples:
فقط بعض الأمثلة:
in Russia, plus 11 after one year,
في روسيا، زادت بنسبة ١١ بعد سنة واحدة
plus 29 after three years of the redesign.
زادت بنسبة ٢٩ بعد ثلاث سنوات من إعادة التصميم
Same in Poland: plus 13, up to 35 percent
وذات الشيء في بولندا: ١٣ زيادة، إلى ٣٥ في المائة
raise of circulation after three years.
زيادة في التوزيع بعد ثلاث سنوات
You can see on a graph,
تستطيع رؤيتها على الرسم البياني
after years of stagnation, the paper started to grow,
بعد سنوات من الركود، الصحيفة بدأت بالنمو
just after redesign.
فقط بعد إعادة التصميم
But the real hit was in Bulgaria.
لكن التغير الكبير كان في بلغاريا
And that is really amazing.
وذلك كان مدهشاً جداً
Did design do this?
هل التصميم فعل ذلك؟
Design was just a part of the process.
التصميم كان فقط جزاءاً من العملية
And the process we made was not about changing the look,
والعملية التي قمنا بها لم تكن عن تغير الشكل فقط
it was about improving the product completely.
كانت عن تطوير المنتج بشكل كامل
I took an architectural rule about function and form
أخذت قانون معماري عن الوظيفة والشكل
and translated it into newspaper content and design.
وترجمته عملياً في مواد الصحيفة وتصميمها
And I put strategy at the top of it.
وقمت بوضع استراتيجية فوق ذلك كله
So first you ask a big question: why we do it? What is the goal?
تسأل نفسك أولاً السؤال الكبير: لماذا نفعل ذلك؟ ما هو الهدف؟
Then we adjust the content accordingly.
ثم يتم تغير المحتوى وفقاً لذلك
And then, usually after two months, we start designing.
وبعد ذلك، عادة بعد شهرين، نقوم بإعادة التصميم
My bosses, in the beginning, were very surprised.
رؤسائي في البداية، كانوا مصدومين
Why am I asking all of these business questions,
لماذا أسأل أسئلة متعلقة عن العمل
instead of just showing them pages?
بدل أن أعرض عليهم صفحات؟
But soon they realized that this is the new role of designer:
لكنهم عاجلاً إكتشفوا أن هذا هو الدور الجديد للمصمم:
to be in this process from the very beginning to the very end.
أن يكون في العملية من البداية حتى النهاية
So what is the lesson behind it?
ما هو الدرس الذي يمكن إستفادته؟
The first lesson is about that design can change not just your product.
الدرس الأول التصميم يستطيع تغير ليس منتجك فقط
It can change your workflow -- actually, it can change everything in your company;
يستطيع تغير سير العمل -- الحقيقة، يستطيع تغير كل شيء في شركتك
it can turn your company upside down.
يستطيع قلب شركتك
It can even change you.
ويستطيع تغيرك أنت أيضاً
And who's responsible? Designers.
ومن هم المسؤولون؟ المصممين
Give power to designers.
أعط المصممين
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But the second is even more important.
لكن الدرس الثاني أكثر أهمية
You can live in a small poor country, like me.
تستطيع العيش في دولة صغيرة وفقيرة، مثلي
You can work for a small company,
تستطيع العيش في شركة صغيرة
in a boring branch.
في فرع ممل
You can have no budgets, no people --
مع انعدام الميزانية، وبدون عمّال -ـ
but still can put your work to the highest possible level.
لكنك تستطيع العمل بأقصى جهد وقدر ممكن
And everybody can do it.
والجميع يمكنهم ذلك
You just need inspiration, vision and determination.
أنت فقط تحتاج للإلهام، الرؤية والعزم
And you need to remember that to be good
وتذكر أن تكون جيدا
is not enough.
غير كافي
Thank you.
شكراً لكم